<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ipekselcen.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ipekselcen.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2026-01-07T17:36:19+00:00</updated><id>https://ipekselcen.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Recent PhD graduate in Biochemistry specializing in epigenetics, chromatin biology, and multi-omics analysis. Bridging wet lab expertise with computational approaches. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tracking Glioblastoma’s Circular DNA at Single-Cell Resolution</title><link href="https://ipekselcen.github.io/blog/2025/glioblastoma-ecdna/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tracking Glioblastoma’s Circular DNA at Single-Cell Resolution"/><published>2025-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ipekselcen.github.io/blog/2025/glioblastoma-ecdna</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ipekselcen.github.io/blog/2025/glioblastoma-ecdna/"><![CDATA[<p>Glioblastoma is the most lethal brain cancer we know, with a median survival under two years even with aggressive treatment. One reason it’s so hard to treat is extrachromosomal DNA, which are circular DNA molecules that carry amplified oncogenes and exist outside the normal chromosomes.</p> <h2 id="the-ecdna-problem">The ecDNA Problem</h2> <p>Extrachromosomal DNA, or ecDNA, shows up in about 50-60% of glioblastomas, making it one of the most ecDNA-rich cancers. These circular DNA molecules typically carry oncogenes such as EGFR, PDGFRA, and CDK4, which are all drivers of aggressive tumor growth. What makes ecDNA particularly dangerous is how it behaves during cell division. Unlike chromosomal DNA, which gets precisely copied and distributed to daughter cells, ecDNA segregates randomly. One daughter cell might inherit many copies while another gets few or none, creating massive cell-to-cell variation in oncogene dosage. This heterogeneity fuels drug resistance and tumor evolution.</p> <p>The problem is that most ecDNA studies have relied on bulk sequencing or imaging approaches that average across thousands of cells, missing this critical heterogeneity. We’ve needed a way to track ecDNA at single-cell resolution in patient samples.</p> <h2 id="what-they-did">What They Did</h2> <p>A team from Soochow University developed scCirclehunter, a computational framework specifically designed to identify ecDNA from single-cell ATAC-seq data. The clever part is how they exploit chromatin accessibility patterns. EcDNA regions show distinctive accessibility signatures because they exist as circles rather than being packed into chromatin like chromosomal DNA. The method uses a pseudo-bulk strategy to first identify candidate ecDNA regions across all cells, then assigns these ecDNAs to specific cell populations using statistical modeling.</p> <p>They applied scCirclehunter to existing glioblastoma scATAC-seq datasets and showed it could reliably detect ecDNA and determine which individual cells carry it. This matters because it finally lets you ask: which tumor cells have ecDNA? How many copies? And what are those cells doing differently?</p> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <p>The analysis revealed striking inter-patient and intra-tumor heterogeneity. Across different glioblastoma patients, ecDNA-carrying cells showed distinct distributions. Some patients had ecDNA throughout most of their tumor, while others showed more patchy distributions. Within a single patient harboring multiple different ecDNAs, they could track separate malignant cell trajectories associated with each ecDNA species. Focusing on ecNR2E1 (an ecDNA carrying the NR2E1 oncogene), they integrated the chromatin accessibility data with matched single-cell RNA-seq to understand how ecDNA affects cellular behavior. The ecDNA didn’t just amplify NR2E1 expression—it drove broader transcriptional programs associated with tumor aggressiveness. Cells carrying ecNR2E1 showed activation of pathways involved in cell proliferation, survival, and immune evasion. An unexpected finding emerged around mitochondrial dynamics. Cells with ecDNA showed evidence of increased mitochondrial transfer, which is a process where cells exchange mitochondria with neighbors. This suggests ecDNA-carrying cells might be manipulating their local environment in ways beyond just overexpressing oncogenes.</p> <h2 id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h2> <p>This work provides a generalizable approach for studying ecDNA heterogeneity in any cancer where scATAC-seq data exists. The single-cell resolution matters clinically because it reveals that ecDNA distribution isn’t uniform: some regions of a tumor might be ecDNA-heavy while others aren’t. This has implications for biopsy sampling, where a single needle biopsy might miss or oversample ecDNA-positive regions, and for understanding why tumors respond heterogeneously to treatment.</p> <p>From a therapeutic standpoint, knowing which cells carry ecDNA and what those cells are doing opens new targeting strategies. Rather than just going after the oncogene itself (such as EGFR inhibitors that often fail in ecDNA-positive tumors), you could potentially target the unique vulnerabilities of ecDNA-carrying cells or the mechanisms that maintain ecDNA.</p> <blockquote class="block-warning"> <h5 id="warning">WARNING</h5> <p>The broader point is methodological: chromatin accessibility data, which many researchers are already generating, contains information about structural genomic alterations like ecDNA that we haven’t been systematically extracting. scCirclehunter provides a way to mine existing datasets for insights into tumor heterogeneity that would otherwise remain hidden.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5> <p><strong>Bottom Line:</strong> Glioblastoma’s circular DNA drives heterogeneity and treatment resistance, but we’ve lacked tools to track it cell-by-cell in patients. Single-cell chromatin accessibility provides a window into which cells carry ecDNA and how that shapes tumor behavior. As ecDNA-targeted therapies move toward the clinic, understanding its distribution at single-cell resolution will be critical for rational treatment design.</p> </blockquote> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Paper:</strong> Jiang et al., <em>Cell Discovery</em> (2024)</td> <td><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41421-025-00842-9">Read the paper →</a></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <ol> <li>Kim H, Nguyen NP, Turner K, et al. Extrachromosomal DNA is associated with oncogene amplification and poor outcome across multiple cancers. Nat Genet. 2020;52:891-897.</li> <li>Bailey C, Pich O, Thol K, et al. Origins and impact of extrachromosomal DNA. Nature. 2024;635:193-200.</li> <li>Lange JT, Rose JC, Chen CY, et al. The evolutionary dynamics of extrachromosomal DNA in human cancers. Nat Genet. 2022;54:1527-1533.</li> <li>Nathanson DA, Gini B, Mottahedeh J, et al. Targeted therapy resistance mediated by dynamic regulation of extrachromosomal mutant EGFR DNA. Science. 2014;343:72-76.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-highlights"/><category term="circular"/><category term="DNA"/><category term="glioblastoma"/><category term="single-cell"/><category term="chromatin"/><category term="research-highlights"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How single-cell epigenomics reveals that Alzheimer's is fundamentally about regulatory collapse, not just protein aggregates]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Epigenomic Breakdown in Alzheimer’s: When Brain Cells Lose Control</title><link href="https://ipekselcen.github.io/blog/2025/alzheimers-epigenomics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Epigenomic Breakdown in Alzheimer’s: When Brain Cells Lose Control"/><published>2025-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ipekselcen.github.io/blog/2025/alzheimers-epigenomics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ipekselcen.github.io/blog/2025/alzheimers-epigenomics/"><![CDATA[<p>Most people think of Alzheimer’s disease in terms of plaques and tangles; the protein clumps that show up in brain scans. But a massive new study published in <em>Cell</em> this September reveals that the real story might be about something more fundamental: brain cells losing their grip on gene regulation itself.</p> <p>We’ve known for a while that Alzheimer’s doesn’t hit all brain regions equally. The hippocampus and entorhinal cortex (your memory centers) get hit early and hard, while other regions like the prefrontal cortex show damage later. But why? And at a cellular level, what’s actually breaking down?</p> <p>This is where single-cell epigenomics comes in. The epigenome (the chemical modifications that control which genes are accessible and which stay locked away) is essentially the instruction manual that tells each cell type how to be itself. When that manual gets corrupted, cells can’t maintain their identity or function properly. Single-cell technologies have revolutionized our ability to map cellular diversity and regulatory landscapes in the brain, but applying them to understand disease progression at this scale is still relatively new.</p> <h2 id="what-they-did">What They Did</h2> <p>The MIT and Broad Institute team, led by Manolis Kellis and Li-Huei Tsai, built the largest single-cell brain atlas for Alzheimer’s to date. They profiled 3.5 million individual cells from 384 postmortem brain samples spanning six different brain regions in 111 donors from the Religious Orders Study and Rush Memory and Aging Project (two well-characterized longitudinal cohort studies that have been instrumental in Alzheimer’s research).</p> <p>The donors ranged from people with no pathology to early-stage and late-stage disease. The key innovation is the integration of single-nucleus ATAC-seq (measuring chromatin accessibility) and single-nucleus RNA-seq (measuring gene expression) in the same tissue samples. This lets you see not just which genes are being expressed, but whether the regulatory machinery controlling those genes is intact or falling apart.</p> <h2 id="the-core-findings">The Core Findings</h2> <p>Two major patterns emerged that fundamentally change how we think about Alzheimer’s progression:</p> <p><strong>First: Epigenome relaxation and compartment breakdown.</strong> Healthy cells maintain strict spatial organization in their nuclei, with the genome partitioned into active and repressive compartments. Active compartments sit in the nuclear interior with accessible chromatin, while repressive compartments are near the nuclear periphery and lamina with higher A/T content.</p> <p>In Alzheimer’s, this organization breaks down. The cells experience what the authors call “epigenomic relaxation”: regions that should be tightly closed become accessible, and active regions lose their structure. Vulnerable neurons in the entorhinal cortex and hippocampus showed the most dramatic compartment switching, with normally repressive chromatin becoming inappropriately activated.</p> <p><strong>Second: Loss of epigenomic information.</strong> Each cell type has a unique epigenetic signature that defines what it is. In Alzheimer’s progression, cells lose this signature. They essentially forget how to be themselves. The study identified over 1 million candidate regulatory elements organized into 123 distinct modules across 67 cell subtypes, and tracked how these modules erode during disease.</p> <p>The loss was most pronounced in excitatory neurons in superficial cortical layers, somatostatin-positive inhibitory interneurons, oligodendrocytes, and microglia.</p> <p>Interestingly, glial cells showed a two-phase response. Early in disease, they gained epigenomic definition as they activated to respond to damage. But with sustained stress, they entered exhausted states and lost their epigenetic stability, especially pronounced in APOE4 carriers.</p> <h2 id="the-resilience-angle">The Resilience Angle</h2> <p>Here’s the hopeful part: some people maintained cognitive function despite having significant Alzheimer’s pathology in their brains. These “resilient” individuals showed something striking: their cells maintained higher epigenomic information across all brain regions compared to people who showed cognitive decline with similar pathology burdens. This suggests that preserving epigenetic stability might be protective, even when plaques and tangles are present.</p> <p>This study shifts the therapeutic conversation. Instead of just targeting plaques and tangles (the end products of disease) we could potentially target the regulatory factors that maintain epigenomic stability. The authors point to Polycomb complexes, which act as “epigenomic guardians” by maintaining chromatin structure. Strengthening these systems, or targeting the specific transcription factors that regulate vulnerable cell types, could offer new intervention strategies.</p> <p>The work complements a companion study published simultaneously in Cell, which found coordinated disruption of 3D genome organization alongside the epigenomic erosion described here. Together, these studies paint a comprehensive picture of how nuclear organization collapses in Alzheimer’s.</p> <p>The dataset itself is also a resource: all data is publicly available, giving the field a detailed molecular map of how different cell types in different brain regions respond to or resist Alzheimer’s pathology.</p> <h2 id="technical-notes">Technical Notes</h2> <p>The study used 10X Genomics platforms for both snATAC-seq (1.2 million nuclei) and snRNA-seq (2.3 million nuclei). They defined epigenomic compartments at genome-wide resolution using hidden Markov models, and calculated epigenomic information for single cells using Shannon entropy, quantifying how well cells maintain their cell-type-specific regulatory programs. Integration across regions and disease stages used Harmony for batch correction, with validation against ENCODE reference datasets.</p> <blockquote class="block-tip"> <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5> <p><strong>Bottom Line:</strong> Alzheimer’s isn’t just about protein aggregates. It’s about a progressive loss of the regulatory control that keeps brain cells functioning. Understanding epigenomic erosion opens new therapeutic avenues and helps explain why some people are resilient while others aren’t. This kind of comprehensive, multimodal atlas is exactly what the field needs to move beyond symptomatic treatments.</p> </blockquote> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Paper:</strong> Liu et al., <em>Cell</em> (2025)</td> <td><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2025.06.031">Read the paper →</a></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <hr/> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <ul> <li>Kelsey G, Stegle O, Reik W. Single-cell epigenomics: Recording the past and predicting the future. <em>Science.</em> 2017;358(6359):69-75.</li> <li>Clark SJ, Lee HJ, Smallwood SA, Kelsey G, Reik W. Single-cell epigenomics: powerful new methods for understanding gene regulation and cell identity. <em>Genome Biol.</em> 2016;17:72.</li> <li>Bennett DA, Schneider JA, Arvanitakis Z, Wilson RS. Overview and findings from the religious orders study. <em>Curr Alzheimer Res.</em> 2012;9(6):628-645.</li> <li>Buenrostro JD, Giresi PG, Zaba LC, Chang HY, Greenleaf WJ. Transposition of native chromatin for fast and sensitive epigenomic profiling of open chromatin, DNA-binding proteins and nucleosome position. <em>Nat Methods.</em> 2013;10(12):1213-1218.</li> <li>Lieberman-Aiden E, van Berkum NL, Williams L, et al. Comprehensive mapping of long-range interactions reveals folding principles of the human genome. <em>Science.</em> 2009;326(5950):289-293.</li> <li>Dixon JR, Selvaraj S, Yue F, et al. Topological domains in mammalian genomes identified by analysis of chromatin interactions. <em>Nature.</em> 2012;485(7398):376-380.</li> <li>Arenaza-Urquijo EM, Vemuri P. Resistance vs resilience to Alzheimer disease: clarifying terminology for preclinical studies. <em>Neurology.</em> 2018;90(15):695-703.</li> <li>Mathys H, Boix CA, Akay LA, et al. Single-cell multiregion dissection of Alzheimer’s disease. <em>Nature.</em> 2024;632:858-868.</li> <li>Korsunsky I, Millard N, Fan J, et al. Fast, sensitive and accurate integration of single-cell data with Harmony. <em>Nat Methods.</em> 2019;16(12):1289-1296.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-highlights"/><category term="epigenomics"/><category term="alzheimers"/><category term="single-cell"/><category term="chromatin"/><category term="research-summary"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How single-cell epigenomics reveals that Alzheimer's is fundamentally about regulatory collapse, not just protein aggregates]]></summary></entry></feed>